<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true Christ, and the Quakers Christ compar'd in a letter sent to Mr. Richard Hardcastle. Wherein is a short review of some things asserted by the Quakers in their Norfolk-disputation with the clergy, &amp;c. 1698. By Robert Prudom.</title>
            <author>Prudom, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220565</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831961</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831961</idno>
            <idno type="VID">36428</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 36428)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2054:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true Christ, and the Quakers Christ compar'd in a letter sent to Mr. Richard Hardcastle. Wherein is a short review of some things asserted by the Quakers in their Norfolk-disputation with the clergy, &amp;c. 1698. By Robert Prudom.</title>
                  <author>Prudom, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Marshal at the Bible in Newgate-street, and John Marshal at the Bible in Gracechurch-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:36428:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The True CHRIST,</hi> And the <hi>Quakers CHRIST compar'd:</hi> IN A LETTER SENT TO Mr. <hi>Richard Hardcaſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is a ſhort Review of ſome things aſſerted by the <hi>Quakers</hi> in their <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk-Diſputation</hi> with the Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1698.</p>
            <p>BY ROBERT PRUDOM.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 24.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wherefore if they ſhall ſay unto you, Behold, he is in the Deſert, go not forth; Behold, he is in the ſecret Chamber, believe them not.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Marſhal</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>John Marſhal</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Gracechurch-ſtreet.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:36428:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:36428:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Richard Hardcaſtle,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Shall not trouble my ſelf with the Jars of theſe two contending Parties, about their prefixing a Meeting; but only recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to thee and others of you, the Truth in the Simplicity of it, and how you are gone from it: which if God ſee good to open your Eyes to behold, I ſhall greatly rejoice.</p>
            <p>I ſhall draw two or three Heads out of this Book, which is, <hi>An Account of a Diſpute betwixt the</hi> Quakers <hi>and the</hi> Clergy <hi>of the Dioceſs of</hi> Norwich; and ſome of your other Writings, which may be of uſe unto thee.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page the 11th of this Book.</bibl> Ever ſince we have been a People gathered by the Power and Spirit of God, we have ſincerely believed, and do ſtill believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as the Holy Scriptures do declare of him; and do not only plainly ſay, but alſo firmly believe, that there is no other name given under Heaven whereby Man can be ſaved; neither is there Salvation in any other name: and this we hope is no Blaſphemy.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page the 15th.</bibl> We believe in God the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth, and in Jeſus Chriſt his only begotten Son our Lord and Saviour, who was born of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:36428:3"/>the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> (whom the Holy Ghoſt overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed) who appeared in the World in that Body pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him; who died for our Sins, and roſe again for our Juſtification: and we believe in the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and own the three that bear Record in Heaven, and that theſe three are one. We own the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of truth, and believe they were given forth by Divine Inſpiration, and that they are profitable for Doctrine, for Correction, for Inſtruction in Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and are able to make the Man of God wiſe unto Salvation, through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus: and we eſteem the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to be the beſt Book in all the World, and could be glad that People did ſpend more of their time in reading of it, and the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, his Baptiſm and the Supper, according to the Holy Scriptures.</q>
            <p>If the Truths laid down in Scripture-words in theſe two Paragraphs were duly kept unto, and the mind of the Spirit of God in them, then would there be no need of charging of Error and Blaſphemy upon that poor deluded People, call'd <hi>Quakers.</hi> But in order to a thorow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of their Errors, and the Truth, in the Spring and Streams that iſſue from it, and how plauſibly they cover deceit, read this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page the 14th</bibl> Speaking of the Prieſts: <hi>For do they not of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice rail upon the Truths of God's Word manifeſtly perceived, and as Enemies thereunto perſecute the ſame, in charging ſo many Blaſphemies upon the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:36428:3"/>Light within? for the Light within is Chriſt: and Chriſt is the truth of God's Word, the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> John 14.6. The Word that was in the beginning with God and was God; <hi>the Sum and Subſtance of the Goſpel, and that which the Holy Scriptures give Teſtimony of, and we believe and teach.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>In order to a clear diſcovery of the Truth in the ſpring of it, and the Streams that come from it, I ſhall lay it down under four Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the true Chriſt preſented unto us in the Holy Scriptures, who is the Object of Faith, is God and Man in one Perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Work of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, in the ſtate of his Humiliation; and the Work of an Interceſſor is, now in the ſtate of his Exaltation, performed by this Chriſt who is God and Man in union, the two Natures of God and Man being concerned in the Work of Redemption and Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Holy Ghoſt's work within be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubſervient to the Bleſſed Mediator with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and leading to the Father through him, doth bring the Soul into an experimental In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That the two Ordinances of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the Supper, do repreſent unto the Faith and viſible Sight of Believers, what Chriſt hath done for them; and that he was a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:36428:4"/>Man dead, buried, and raiſed again from the dead, and he is now exiſtent in our human Nature in Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the true Chriſt preſented to us in the Holy Scriptures, who is the immediate Object of our Faith, is God and Man in one Perſon, dos appear in that, when we have an account of his Perſon in the Old or New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, we have his Manhood join'd to the Divine Nature, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. Many Scriptures do give the Name CHRIST alone to his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, not thereby to exclude his Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.25, 26. <hi>Then he ſaid unto them, O Fools and ſlow of heart to believe all that the Prophets have ſpoken; Ought not Chriſt to have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered theſe things, and to enter into his Glory?</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Acts</hi> 2.36. <hi>Therefore let all the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>know aſſuredly, that God hath made that ſame Jeſus whom ye have crucified both Lord and Chriſt.</hi> Whenever the Holy Scripture doth ſpeak of him in his Divine Nature, it leaves not off the Diſcourſe, but by the hand doth lead us to his Manhood: <hi>John</hi> 1.1, to 13. he ſpeaks of his Divine Nature; in <hi>v.</hi> 14. he takes in the Manhood; <hi>And the Word was made Fleſh, and dwelt amongſt us; and we beheld his Glory, the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as of the only begotten of the Father, full of Grace and Truth;</hi> compared with <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.5, to 12. <hi>Let this Mind be in you, which alſo was in Chriſt Jeſus; who being in the Form of God, thought it not Robbery to be equal with God</hi> (as to his Divine Nature) <hi>but made himſelf of no reputation, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:36428:4"/>took upon him the Form of a Servant, and was made in the likeneſs of Men: And being found in faſhion as a Man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto the death, even the death of the Croſs: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath highly exalted him, and given him a Name which is above every Name, that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow, of things in Heaven, and things in Earth, and things under the Earth: And every Tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus is the Chriſt, to the Glory of God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Work of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was in the ſtate of his Humiliation, and the Work of an Interceſſor is in the ſtate of his Exaltation, performed by this Chriſt who is God and Man in one Perſon, the two Natures of God and Man being concerned in the Work of Redemption and Interceſſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall divide this Head into two parts; 1. Shew that the Work of our Redemption was wrought out in the ſtate of Chriſt's Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, performed by him as God and Man in Union, the two Natures in that Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concerned in this Work.</p>
            <p>Iſa 53.11, 12. <hi>He ſhall ſee of the Travail of his Soul, and ſhall be ſatisfied: By his Knowledg ſhall my righteous Servant juſtify many, for he ſhall bear their Iniquities. Therefore will I divide him a Portion with the great, and he ſhall divide the Spoil with the ſtrong, becauſe he hath poured out his Soul unto death, and he was numbered with the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors;</hi> compared with 1 Tim. 2.16. <hi>And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſy, great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs, God was manifeſted in the Fleſh, juſtified in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:36428:5"/>The firſt Scripture gives us an account how the Manhood was concerned in the Work in ſuffering for Sinners; and therefore he ſhould ſee the travail of his Soul in bearing part in that Honour due to the Redeemer. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Scripture ſhews us how the Divine Nature perfumed his Sufferings, in order to their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with the Father, for the Perſons for whom he ſuffered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Work of an Interceſſor is perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed now in the ſtate of his Exaltation, by this Chriſt who is God and Man, the two Natures of God and Man being concerned in the Work, Rom. 1.4. <hi>And declared the Son of God with Power, according to the Spirit of Holineſs</hi> (which was his Divine Nature) <hi>by the Reſurrection from the dead; by whom we have received Grace and Apoſtleſhip;</hi> that is, the Qualifications for that great Work, belonging to that great Office. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.32, 33. <hi>This Jeſus hath God raiſed up, whereof we all are Witneſſes. Therefore being by the right hand of God exalted, and having received of the Father the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt, he hath ſhed forth this which ye now ſee and hear.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.6. <hi>For there is one God, and one Mediator betwixt God and Men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Holy Ghoſt's work within being ſubſervient to the bleſſed Mediator without, and leading to the Father through him, brings the Soul into an experimental Injoyment of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; <hi>John</hi> 15.26, 27. <hi>But when the Comforter is come, whom I will ſend unto you from the Father, even the Spirit of Truth, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:36428:5"/>proceedeth from the Father, He ſhall teſtify of me. And ye alſo ſhall bear witneſs, becauſe ye have been with me from the beginning.</hi> What was the Sum and Subſtance of the Apoſtle's Doctrine? Even to recommend this Redeemer the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his Perſon and Sufferings to Sinners, Rom. 10.9. <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſs with thy Mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thy Heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> What is the Sum and Subſtance of the Holy Ghoſt's Work within? Even to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany this outward Declaration of the Goſpel; opening the Underſtanding of poor Sinners; letting them ſee the need of a Saviour; ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Heart to cloſe with him, and by faith to lay hold of that Grace which comes from the Father through him. The inward Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Father and the Sons Love to us is by the Spirit; and it is the Spirit's work to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the Fire of Love more and more in the Souls of Saints, by which through the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mediator, they are inabled to offer up their Souls to their heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The two Ordinances of Baptiſm, and the Supper, do repreſent unto the Faith of Believers what Chriſt hath done for them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they both point at his Perſon, and what he hath done in his Human Nature, buried in the Grave for them, held forth by Water. Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. Doth Bread and Wine ſupport, by feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it, the outward Man? So doth the Fleſh and Blood of the Man Chriſt, through that Vertue which the Divine Nature puts into
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:36428:6"/>it, tend to feed the Inward; <hi>My Fleſh,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is Meat indeed, and my Blood is Drink indeed.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>For as often as ye eat this Bread and drinks this Cup</hi> (ſpeaking of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Ordinance) <hi>ye ſhew the Lord's Death till he come.</hi> Doth it point at him that died, and is riſen and come in Spirit? then, <hi>until he come,</hi> muſt refer to his ſecond perſonal Appearance, as a glorified Man, to judg the World: <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31. <hi>Becauſe he hath appointed a day, in the which he will judg the World in Righteouſneſs, by that Man whom he hath ordained; whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all Men, in that he hath raiſed him from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I come to ſpeak of this Spiritual Chriſt, as he is worſhipped by this poor deceived People, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are greatly impoſed upon by their Leaders, for want of bringing their Writings to be ſeriouſly examined by the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And firſt as to his Perſon, we have him in their Writings repreſented as a Spirit, and as ſuch Divine Honour given to him.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly,</hi> The Work of Redemption not brought in a way of ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice for ſin, but in the way of the firſt Covenant, of Do this and live, <hi>i.e.</hi> Obey the Light within and live.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly,</hi> Acceptance with God not bottom'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Mediator without us, but an interceding Spirit within.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as to his Perſon; we have him in their Writings preſented as a Spirit, and as ſuch Divine Honour given to him: This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:36428:6"/>pears in the moſt of their Books; but I ſhall at this time only mention two; the firſt taken out of the 14th Page of this Book, which is, <hi>An Account of a Diſpute betwixt the</hi> Clergy <hi>of the Dioceſs of</hi> Norwich <hi>in</hi> Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 98. <hi>and the People called</hi> Quakers. Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prieſts: <hi>For do they not of malice rail upon the Truths of God's Word manifeſtly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and as Enemies thereunto perſecute the ſame, in charging ſo many Blaſphemies upon the Light within? for the Light within is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>William Pen<hi>'s</hi> Chriſtian Quaker, pag. 97, 98. <hi>The Body of Chriſt is not ſo much as in any one, and conſequently the Seed of the Promiſe is an holy and ſpiritual Principle of Light, Liſe, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Power, that being received into the Heart, bruiſeth the Serpent's Head; and becauſe the Seed which cannot be that Body is Chriſt, as teſtify the Scriptures, the Seed is one, and that Seed Chriſt, and Chriſt God over all bleſſed for ever: We do conclude, and that moſt truly, that Chriſt was and is the Divine Word of Light and Life that was in the beginning with God, and was and is God over all bleſſed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to theſe Paragraphs, it is evident and plain, that whatever confeſſion is made by this People of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as born of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> they do not intend that the Body which was formed in the Womb of the Virgin, by the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt, doth ſhare with the Eternal Word, Creator, in the conſtituting of Chriſt, and partakes with the Divine Nature in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:36428:7"/>Honour: and yet this poor deluded Man who hath been an Inſtrument to lead many ſober Perſons into grievous Errors, hath the Confidence in his Book to tell us, that he is of the ſame Faith with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs that ſuffer'd in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days; which if he can bring one inſtance of any of the Martyrs; in any of their Writings that exclude the Human Nature in union with the Divine, from being the true Chriſt of God, I will be willing to make a publick Recantation, that I have greatly wronged the <hi>Quakers.</hi> The true Chriſt was conceived in the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin's Womb, and lay in the Grave: But he tells us that the Seed is one, as ſaith the Scripture, (intending only the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or rather the Light of natural Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in all Men) <hi>Pag.</hi> 98. of his <hi>Chriſtian Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker;</hi> and in the Margin of the Book he directs us to <hi>Gal</hi> 3.16. Now, Reader, let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thee in the Fear of the Lord, and as thou wiſheſt the Welfare of thy immortal Soul, that thou ſeriouſly weigh this Scripture, and ſee if thou canſt find any thing in it for the excluding of the Human Nature from having a ſhare to conſtitute Chriſt; <hi>Now to</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham <hi>and his Seed were the Promiſes made: He ſaith not to ſeeds, as of many; but as of one, And to thy Seed, which is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here in this Scripture <hi>Abraham,</hi> an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Believer, and thoſe that are of the ſame Faith with him, are promiſed eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by God; here is the one Seed by way of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:36428:7"/>eminence ſet above all the reſt; (but then mark it well this one Seed ſhall be thy Seed, <hi>Abraham.</hi>) Moreover he is ſaid to be the Seed of <hi>David</hi> according to the Fleſh. Reader, make uſe of thy Underſtanding, and judg whether by <hi>thy own Seed, Abraham,</hi> be meant a Principle of Light, Life, and Power, or is meant that Man which the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> brought forth in the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> and who was ſeen with natural Eyes: if the latter be meant, thou mayſt then ſee the door by which an erroneous Spirit hath led ſo many from the Foundation of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>But ſaith <hi>William Pen, The Body of Chriſt is not ſo much as in any one.</hi> And another Quaker ſaith, <hi>The true Chriſt was never ſeen of bodily Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and what Chriſt faith to the Man whoſe Eyes he opened, Joh. 9. <hi>Doſt thou believe on the Son of God?</hi> To whom he replyed, <hi>who is he, Lord?</hi> See our Saviour's Anſwer; <hi>Thou haſt both ſeen him, and he it is that ſpeaketh to thee.</hi> Alſo God <hi>ſware to</hi> David, <hi>that of the Fruit of his Loins according to the Fleſh he would raiſe up Chriſt to ſit upon his Throne.</hi> Will they render God guilty of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury? it muſt be ſo if Chriſt be not truly of <hi>David</hi>'s Seed according to the Fleſh. See <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Wherefore ſeeing we are compaſſed about with ſo great a Cloud of Witneſſes, let us lay aſide every weight and the Sin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us, and let us run with patience the Race that is ſet before us, looking unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher of our,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:36428:8"/>Faith; who for the Joy that was ſet before him, endured the Croſs, deſpiſing the Shame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi> This Cloud of Witneſſes are the Saints from <hi>Abel,</hi> recorded in the 11th Chapter, who in the Promiſes of a Saviour to come through the Spirit's Work upon the Heart, were by Faith led to behold him, and inabled to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor upon the Immutability and Unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of the Promiſes concerning him, ſo often renew'd in the Old Teſtament unto the Fathers: ſo that this poor deceived Man, <hi>William Pen,</hi> doth not diſtinguiſh betwixt a perſonal Injoyment of him within, and an Injoyment of him within by Faith. If a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Injoyment of him within were intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then indeed it would exclude the Human Nature from ſharing with the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in conſtituting Chriſt; but the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture when it ſpeaks of Chriſt, it ſpeaks of him as perſonally abſent, but preſent by Faith, and by his Spirit: and with this agree the Experiences of Saints, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>For I am in a ſtrait betwixt two, having a deſire to depart and to be with Chriſt, which is far better;</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Whom having not ſeen ye love, in whom though now ye ſee him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy unſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi> Our dear Lord in that viſionary Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which he gives of himſelf to <hi>John,</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.17, 18. doth with great clearneſs hold forth his two Natures to us; —<hi>Fear not, I am the firſt and the laſt; I am he that liveth and was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:36428:8"/>dead, and behold I am alive for evermore.</hi> Was the Eternal Word, the Divine Nature of the Lord Jeſus, ever dead? if not, he is ſpeaking of his Human Nature. I have ſtaid the longer upon this Head, that I might clear up the Foundation of Chriſtianity, and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Son of God in that Honour which is confer'd upon him as God-man againſt this Erroneous Spirit, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the pretence of the ſetting up of a ſpiritual Kingdom, is from their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, as to the Work upon the Heart, no other than the firſt Covenant Light, which gives no diſcovery of the Goſpel Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and which a <hi>Mahometan</hi> or <hi>Indian</hi> hath in common with them <hi>Sam. Fiſher</hi>'s <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Truth exalted,</hi> p. 696. as recorded by Squire <hi>Edwards</hi> in his Book of <hi>Baxterianiſm Barefac'd.</hi>
               <q>Is the Light in <hi>America</hi> then any more inſufficient to lead its Followers, than the Light in <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Africa,</hi> the other three parts of the World? I have ever look'd upon the Light in all Men (ſince I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to look at it in myſelf) as one and the ſame Light in all.</q> 
               <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſaith true; for the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the ſober Gentiles, <hi>Socrates, Pythagoras,</hi> and others of them, if compared, will anſwer one another, as Face anſwers Face in a Glaſs, with this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; Satan in the poor <hi>Quakers</hi> ſheltering himſelf under the Convictions of the Law, doth by deceivableneſs ſeek to rob the Son of God of his Honour, nay of his Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:36428:9"/>
               <hi>2ly,</hi> We have this ſpiritual Chriſt, or Light in all, bringing in the Work of Redemption, not in a way of ſatisfaction to Divine Juſtice for ſin, but in a way of the firſt Covenant, Obey and live. Mr. <hi>Barclay</hi> a <hi>Scots-Quaker,</hi> in his <hi>Apology for the People call'd Quakers,</hi> p. 91. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd with <hi>p.</hi> 90. <hi>The Light within takes away all ground of deſpair, in that it gives every one ground of hope and certain aſſurance that they may be ſaved; neither doth feed any in ſecurity, in that none are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain how ſoon their day may expire; and therefore it is a conſtant Incitement and Provocation, and lively Incouragement to every man to forſake evil, and cloſe with that which is good;</hi> compared with <hi>William Pen</hi>'s <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> p. 97. <hi>The Serpent is a Spirit.</hi> Now nothing can bruiſe the Head of the Serpent, but ſomething that is alſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and ſpiritual, as the Serpent is.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to theſe two Paragraphs, I ſay that the drift of theſe Words turns the Work of Redemption quite out of the Goſpel-Channel, and takes down the two main Pillars upon which it ſtands; which was a transferring our Sins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs upon us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>For he hath made him to be ſin for us, who knew no ſin, that we might be made the Righteonſneſs of God in him.</hi> What ground of hope, and certain aſſurance of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation their obedience to the Light, which convinceth of ſin, will afford them, if they could but have a view of their ſtate in the glaſs of the holy Law of God, deſerves their moſt ſerious conſideration: For upon their own
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:36428:9"/>Principles without Perfection, no Salvation; and yet hardly any of them ſo hardy, as to ſay they have attain'd it. Their Doctrine may ſute a Self righteous Perſon, but will not go down with a heavy-laden Sinner, neither a humble Saint; both theſe by Faith are led to cloſe with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt for Salvation, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowlege it their Mercy, that they have ſuch good ſecurity in another, when they find ſo little in themſelves. <hi>To him that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, his Faith is counted for Righteouſneſs.</hi> The Perſons that come for Salvation in the Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, come to Chriſt as ſenſible Sinners, and as ſuch to the Footſtool of Grace; and yet at the ſame time are preſſing after a ſincere Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in a way of Duty yet ſenſibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with much Imperfection.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. tells me it is by the death Chriſt that Satan's Power is taken away, which I take to be a bruiſing of his Head, a Door of entrance into Heaven being thereby open'd another way than by Man's imperfect Obedience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19. <hi>William Pen</hi>'s blind Reaſon is as oppoſite to Faith, as Light and Darkneſs, and ſees not how <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15. points at the bleſſed Jeſus, as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Head overcoming Satan, for all his myſtical Body.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This ſpiritual Chriſt placeth our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God not upon a Mediator with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but an interceding Spirit within. <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pen</hi>'s <hi>Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> p. 101. <hi>As at any time diſobedient Men have hearkened to the ſtill
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:36428:10"/>voice of the Word (that Meſſenger of God in their Hearts) to be affected and convinced by it, as it brings reproof for Sin, which is but a fatherly Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement; ſo upon true brokenneſs of Soul and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition of Spirit, that very Principle and Word of Life in Man hath mediated and atoned, and God hath been propitious, lifting up the Light of his Countenance, and repleniſhing ſuch humble Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents with Divine Conſolations: So that ſtill the ſame Chriſt, Word, God, who hath inlightned all men, by Sin is grieved, bearing the Iniquities of ſuch as ſin, and reject his Benefits; but as any hear his Knocks, and let him in, he firſt wounds, and then heals; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards atones, mediates, and reinſtates in the holy Image; behold, this is the ſtate of Reſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to <hi>William Pen.</hi> If Scripture-Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may take place, we may ſee here how the Mediatorſhip of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt as God-man, now in his exalted State at the right hand of the Father, is invaded by a lying Spirit: the Apoſtle in <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.18. ſaith, <hi>Through him we</hi> (both Jew and Gentile) <hi>have an acceſs by one Spirit unto the Father.</hi> As the Holy Ghoſt is ſent forth from the Father, through the Interceſſion of the Son, as God-Man now at his right hand in Glory: ſo his Work is ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to the Mediator. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowleges the Spirit to be ſent this way, and how the Manhood of Chriſt was concerned in ſending him, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.32, 33. <hi>This Jeſus hath God raiſed up</hi> (who in the former Verſes he tells us, was laid in the Sepulcher) <hi>whereof we all are Witneſſes: Therefore being exalted, and having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Father the Promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:36428:10"/>he hath ſhed forth that which we now ſee and hear.</hi> The Apoſtle to <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24, 25. incourageth Perſons to go to God the Father by Faith, through this bleſſed exalted Mediator; and that becauſe they have this Incouragement, of his continuing in his Prieſthood; and that his Interceſſion is of ſuch a prevailing nature, that thoſe that come to him ſhall be ſaved to the uttermoſt by him: But this Man conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth ever.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now draw a few heads in order to compare <hi>William. Pen</hi>'s Chriſt, and the true Chriſt, one with the other: <hi>William Pen</hi>'s Chriſt is a Spirit within; the Saints Chriſt is an exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God-man in Heaven, who by his interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Father, hath the Holy Ghoſt now on Earth ſubſervient to him, to manifeſt him to the Hearts of his People. <hi>William Pen</hi>'s Chriſt is a Spirit who bears the Iniquities of his, People within; the Saints Chriſt bore the Iniquities of his People without in his Body upon the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and now bears their Perſons before the Father in Glory. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Pen</hi>'s Chriſt is already come; and with Contempt treads down the two Ordinances of Water-Baptiſm, and the Supper, which the true Chriſt left his Church until his ſecond perſonal Appearance. The true Chriſt is yet to come, and when he comes, as ſaith the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>ſhall deſcend from Heaven with a Shout, with the voice of the Archangel, and with the Trump of God, and the Dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt;</hi> and that we may know whereabouts we are, take a view of Chriſt's word's, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.26.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:36428:11"/>— <hi>he is in the ſecret Chambers, believe them not.</hi> A Chriſt within, ſet up to oppoſe a Chriſt without; and to bear away thoſe Inſigns of Honour due to the true Saviour. For the ſcene that is acted next, I leave to the Reader's Meditation, <hi>ver.</hi> 27. <hi>For as the Lightning cometh out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth unto the Weſt; even ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of Man be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take but a ſerious view of the Books of the People call'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> and we may clearly ſee that whatever Confeſſions they may make to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Goſpel-Truths in agreeing with other Chriſtians; it is but as a Blind or Cover to keep thoſe ſpiritual Deluſions, which they are carried away withal, from being diſcovered. It may be thought that I have ſuck'd in ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt their Perſons, but the Searcher of hearts knows 'tis otherwiſe; its only in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and faithfulneſs to God who hath, to the praiſe of his rich Grace, inlightned my Soul with Goſpel-Light and Love to their Souls, and the Souls of others, that I deal thus plainly with them. And ſo what I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I recommend to thee my Friend in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and all others who may come to the fight of it; ſearch it throughly by the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; only let me tell thee, the Author hath no Eloquence to allure thee, it is only the Truth in its native Beauty that he preſents unto thee; ſo that it is the truth it ſelf that muſt take thee if thou be taken, and not the manner in which it is preſented.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:36428:11"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>NO Errors are more dangerous, than to <hi>deny the Lord that bought us;</hi> for ſuch are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and they that hold them are guilty of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and <hi>bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. The <hi>Socinians</hi> ſay that Chriſt is a mere Man, and that he had no Being or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence before he was conceived and born of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> and ſo utterly deny he is the Moſt High God. The <hi>Arians</hi> aſſert Chriſt was the firſt and moſt glorious Spirit which God made, and that Spirit they affirm (as I think) did aſſume our Nature in the Womb of the <hi>Virgin.</hi> We have alſo other Hereticks raiſed up among us, who I hear are headed by one <hi>Matthew Caffin,</hi> and ſwarm in <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Suſſex,</hi> who ſeem to favour the <hi>Arians,</hi> but with this difference; theſe ſeem to ſay, that that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was converted into a ſort of Fleſh, or was made Fleſh in the Virgin's Womb, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took not of her Subſtance, ſo that they deny both his Divine and Human Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he is not God of the Eſſence of the Father, nor Man of the Subſtance of <hi>Mary;</hi> not the Moſt High God, tho he be a God; yet a leſſer, or <hi>Demi-god;</hi> a God by Office only, and not God by Nature. The <hi>Euti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chians</hi> hold that the Divinity or Godhead was turned into Fleſh, and this I hear <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffin</hi> once aſſerted. The <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay that Chriſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:36428:12"/>is the Light, which is in all Men, the ſame in <hi>Turks, Pagans,</hi> as thoſe called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> which is nothing more nor leſs than an inward quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Light flowing from Chriſt, conſidered as Creator, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. and it is the Subſtance of the Law that was given to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which Law the <hi>Gentiles</hi> having not in that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration in two Tables of Stone, have it writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in their Hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.15. Now evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent it is, that all theſe deny the true Chriſt, or Chriſt of God, <hi>i. e.</hi> God-man, or God with us, God in our Nature. I having only now to do with this laſt ſort, ſhall add a little more to diſcover their deceit, who whilſt they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to own him to be the Chriſt who died on the Croſs, it may appear evident to all they mean no ſuch matter; for they own no other thing to be Chriſt but that Light which is in all Men, which is no body of Fleſh. True, they own that which died was his Body, <hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſt dwelt eminently in him; but that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, faith <hi>Pen,</hi> is in no Man, <hi>ergo</hi> that can't be the Chriſt in his Senſe which is incapable to dwell in Men. Now, <hi>Reader,</hi> conſider that Chriſt was one of our Brethren, and that the Divine Nature took on him the ſame Fleſh and Blood the Children have, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14.15. that he was <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and the Seed of <hi>David</hi> according to the Fleſh; and tho <hi>David</hi>'s Lord as to his Divine Nature, yet <hi>David</hi>'s Son as to his Human Nature, and ſo the <hi>Root and Off ſpring of</hi> David. But if what theſe Men ſay be true, then Chriſt did not die, for that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:36428:12"/>could not be the Chriſt that died, becauſe that Body could not be in any Man, Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only a Spirit in their judgment. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays Chriſt died according to the Scripture: I might mention I think 30 or 40 Scriptures that affirm that Chriſt died for our Sins, and that he that died was the Son of God; becauſe his Human and Divine Nature make but one Perſon. We ſay ſuch a Man died, but we do not mean his Soul died; ſo we do not ſay the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture died that was impaſſible, yet it is as true that Chriſt died, as to ſay that <hi>Thomas</hi> or <hi>John</hi> died. But now did the Light within die? Did that bear our Sins on its Body on the Tree? Did the Light within ſhed its Blood to ſatisfy God's Juſtice? Was the Light within con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and born of the Virgin, crucified, dead, buried and raiſed again? Did the Light within aſcend to Heaven, and ſits now at the Father's right hand, to make interceſſion for us? All this is affirmed in the Holy Scripture of the Chriſt of God; therefore the Quakers Chriſt is none of God's Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay they own him to be the Chriſt that was born of the Virgin, yet affirm the true Chriſt is the Light within all Men, and that he was never ſeen with any outward bodily Eyes; and that that Body was called Chriſt, becauſe the true Chriſt was in him: Why then may not they be called Chriſt, for he, they ſay, is in them? Is it not ſtrange they ſhould give ſuch a plauſible Confeſſion of their Faith, as is written in the beginning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:36428:13"/>of this Letter, and yet do often declare quite contrary Doctrine, <hi>viz. What good can a Chriſt without do us? Let us mind the Light within, that is enough for us, and not trouble our ſelves with a Chriſt without:</hi> See <hi>Margaret Everard</hi>'s late Sheet, <hi>page</hi> 2, 3. who was a great Preacher among them for many years, but is now ſaved out of the Snare of the Devil. Alſo further ſhe ſays, <hi>They call the preaching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt without Wiſdom, and feeding upon the Tree of Knowledg, and Scripture-notions, and that they did not mind Scripture-notions.</hi> 2. They ſay they believe the Scriptures to be of Divine Authority, yet deny them to be the Rule of our Faith and Practice. 3. They ſay they own Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper, yet deny Water-baptiſm, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn breaking of Bread and drinking of Wine in remembrance of Chriſt's Death, and call both carnal and beggarly Elements. 4. They ſay they deny not Juſtification by Chriſt, but own it; <q>But we do deny, ſay they, Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by that Man or Perſon that died, that his Righteouſneſs wrought without us ſhould juſtify us.</q> Thus <hi>Pen.</hi> 5. They ſay they own the Reſurrection of the dead, yet deny that that Body that is buried in the Grave of the Earth, ſhall ever riſe again; they mean other things, and like the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have their <hi>Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations,</hi> and <hi>mental Reſervations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> And as they who deny Chriſt to be God and Man in one Perſon, do deny the Lord that bought them: ſo from hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows they muſt be guilty of other Hereſies,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:36428:13"/>nay of Idolatry, and Blaſphemy alſo; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They deny Chriſt's Satisfaction, and the Imputation of his Obedience or Righteouſneſs, as the material Cauſe of our Juſtification be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, as apprehended by Faith alone, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Satisfaction depends on the Worth and Dignity of his Perſon, he being God in our Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They aſſert, <q>Unleſs we become Doers of that Law which Chriſt came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but to fulfil, as our Example, we can never be juſtified before God; nor (ſay they) let not any fancy that Chriſt hath ſo fulfilled it for them, as to exclude their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from being requiſite to their accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but only as their Pattern.</q> 
               <hi>Pen</hi>'s <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Foundation,</hi> p. 26.</p>
            <p>If it be our own Righteouſneſs by keeping the Law that juſtifies us, why do they call this the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, who, as they ſay, only kept the Law as our Pattern and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? and how is it then true which <hi>Paul</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>i. e. By the Righteouſneſs which is of the Law, no Fleſh can be juſtified in God's ſight?</hi> Rom. 3.20. Moreover, how is it true that <hi>as by the diſobedience of one man, many were made ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſo by the obedience of one, many ſhall be made righteous,</hi> Rom. 5.19. If it be by every ones own Obedience to the Law or Light within, it is then not of one, but of many: and how doth <hi>Paul</hi> come to ſay, <hi>He was made ſin for us that knew no Sin, that we might be made the righteouſneſs of God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:36428:14"/>in him?</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. Alſo in vain then were all thoſe typical Atonements, and expiatory Sacrifices for Sin under the Law; nor has Chriſt <hi>by one Offering put away ſin,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by the Blood of his Croſs.</hi> Nor are all our Works, whether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal or external, excluded in point of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. They ſay they are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt; but they mean the Righteouſneſs wrought in their own Perſons by their Chriſt within, which is the Law within, and ſo ſtill 'tis by the Law. Their evil Doctrine renders the whole deſign of God in our bleſſed Mediator Jeſus Chriſt (in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the World, in his taking our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on him, and in his Body to work to bring in a Righteouſneſs in obedience to the Law, and in his Death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>)vain, and of none effect.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They ſeek Juſtification by the Law, <hi>i. e.</hi> by their Obedience to the Light within them, which is (as I ſaid) but the Law of the firſt Covenant, or Law written in two Tables of Stone, as to the Subſtance of it, which is alſo much darkned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They juſtify the Jews who charged our Lord with Blaſphemy, for ſaying he was the Son of God, and ſo made himſelf equal with God.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They give ſpiritual Worſhip or Divine Adoration, due to God only, to a mere Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The <hi>Quakers</hi> give no Divine Worſhip to <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> not to him, but to a Chriſt within, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Light or Law in their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:36428:14"/>Hearts. Pray read theſe Scriptures, and I'll conclude; <hi>Thou ſhalt conceive and bare a Son, and ſhalt call his name Jeſus; he ſhall be great, and ſhall be called the Son of the Higheſt: unto you is born this day in the City of</hi> David, <hi>a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord:</hi> Mark it, <hi>which, is Chriſt,</hi> not the Light in him, Chriſt ſignifies the Anointed, the Spirit is the anointing. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith the Woman of <hi>Samaria) the Meſſiah ſhall come; Jeſus; ſaith unto her, I that ſpeaks unto thee am he,</hi> Joh. 4.25, 26. <hi>Who do Men ſay I the Son of Man am?</hi> — <hi>But who doſt thou ſay I am? Thou art Chriſt</hi> (there is his human Nature) <hi>the Son of the living God:</hi> There is his Divine Nature owned; and upon this Faith, this Chriſt, as thus owned, he ſays he will build his Church, <hi>&amp;c. Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> affirmed that <hi>God had made that ſame Jeſus whom the Jews crucified, both Lord and Chriſt,</hi> Acts 2.36. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms that all that would be ſaved, <hi>muſt keep in remembrance what he had preached, unleſs they believed in vain;</hi> which was firſt <hi>how Chriſt died for our Sins according to the Scriptures, and that he was buried, and roſe again the third day,</hi> — <hi>and that he was ſeen of many,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.3, 4. Can this be ſaid of the Light within? The true Church is built upon this Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> that <hi>Chriſt is the Son of Man, made of a Woman,</hi> and yet the <hi>Son of the Living God,</hi> or God of the Eſſence of the Father, or his Son by an eternal Generation, <hi>who thought it not Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to be equal with God:</hi> So that thoſe Churches that are not built on this Faith, are falſe Churches, and their Teachers but Deceivers
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:36428:15"/>and Impoſtors. O what an age are we in, what Errors abound among us! Beware Friend, thou art not deceived. And let ſuch alſo take heed, who tho they own Chriſt's Perſon, yet deny Juſtification by his Righteouſneſs, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Active and Paſſive Obedience, as the only matter or material cauſe of it; but ſecretly bring in with others, <hi>a Popiſh Doctrine,</hi> viz. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by a new Law of Grace,</hi> or by their Faith and ſincere Obedience. The <hi>Quakers</hi> may as ſoon be juſtified by the Law or Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the <hi>Jews</hi> by the Law written in Stone, and the moralized Perſon by liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſober Life, as they can be juſtified by their new Law: <hi>For if righteouſneſs come by the Law, Chriſt is dead in vain,</hi> Gal. 2.21. by any Law either within us, or without us, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in either the Old or New Teſtament: <hi>If it be of Works, it is not of Grace,</hi> Rom. 11.6. all Works done in us, or by us are excluded, that all boaſting might be excluded, and God in Chriſt, and free Grace exalted. Now to the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, be <hi>Glory and eternal Praiſes for ever and ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>F I N I S.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>THere is in the preſs, A ſhort Survey of the Kingdom of Chriſt here on Earth with his Saints; in which the New Heavens and New Earth, the Reſtoration of all things, and other important matters are clearly handled. By way of Supplement to a Tract lately publiſh'd, call'd, <hi>The Myſteries of God finiſh'd,</hi> by the ſame Author, and proper to be ſtitch'd up with it. <hi>Price 6 d,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
